A Finding Aid to the Robert Wiegand papers and video art, 1953-1994, in the Archives of American Art AAA.wiegrobe
Archives of American Art
- Photographs, 1953-1994; Series 6; 1 Linear feet
  - Photographs of Studio, 1994 May (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Master Slides of Artworks, 1954-1989 (Box 5, Folder 8-12, Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Slides of "Bicentennial Banners" (1976) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Slides of Later Artworks, 1977-1990 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Slides of "The Buffalo Statement", 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Slides for Teaching, circa 1961-1971 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Duplicate Slides of Artworks, 1957-1989 (Box 6, Folder 6-8)
- Other Video Recordings, circa 1975-1989; Series 7; 4 Linear feet
  This series contains video recordings that are neither Wiegand's artworks or personal recordings, but other types of recordings he produced, as well as a few tapes made both others found with his papers. Categories of recordings in the series are industry productions, independent projects, performance documentation, work samples, and works by others.
  Industry productions are mainly educational and training videos made for companies such as IBM, Dynalloy Company, DJR Associates, and the American Society of Mechanical Engineers. Also found is a tape made for the New York State Higher Education Opportunity Program called The Sentence II. Wiegand's process involved using low quality video equipment to storyboard and write scripts in the pre-production phase, and these tapes are found among the finished projects, along with occasional paper documentation.
  Independent projects include unedited footage, excerpts, and finished programs that Wiegand created for small organizations and individuals. Notable projects include Bob Towbin's B-Day Special, a home-movie-artwork hybrid video created by Ingrid and Robert for Bob Towbin's 35th birthday, The Night Before The Night Before Christmas, a project produced by Wiegand that aired on DCTV, an Arts Mag episode produced by Ingrid Wiegand, and clips of Angelique Martin's talk show, edited by Robert Wiegand. Wiegand also shot, edited and produced Pamela Stockwell's reenactment of the Tompkins Square Riot. All the unedited footage of the reenactment, in addition to the finished edited piece, are in this series. The printed materials series contains paper documentation related to a few of these videos.
  Performance documentation contains video of performing artists Trisha Brown, Leonard Horowitz, Carolee Schneeman, and Laura Foreman, among others, and four compilation tapes of performances Wiegand shot. Trisha Brown's Line-Up performance also includes an interview with her. Eight hours of raw footage of performances at the East Village performance club, ABC No Rio, are also found.
  Work samples include compilation clips of Wiegand's works. They were used for teaching and soliciting production work. The first two videos are components of a single work, video and narration, yet neither of them are an edit master. Works by others include two tapes that are tools Wiegand may have used in the creation of his videos, a calibration tape and a sales tape for a video title making tool. Eyes on the Prize is an off-air taping of the well-known documentary.
  - Industry Productions (Box 6)
    - International Business Machines, Ideas... Another Opportunity, 1981; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Duration 15 minutes; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate; labeled "IBM" (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - New York University, The Sentence I, circa 1985; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate; labeled "IBM"; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Duration 60 minutes (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Tenba Bag Corporation, Tenba Bag, circa 1985; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) label reads "First Part Tenba" (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Dynalloy Company, Killian Set-Up, 1981 January 13; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Includes paper documentation explaining the training video (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - DJR Associates, FMS 80/81, 1982; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Duration 60 minutes tape has a label from 'Intercontinental Televideo'; checked boxes include NTSC, 525, and Duplicate (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Bergwall Productions, Basic Electricity, circa 1985; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate; labeled "IBM"; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Duration 20 minutes on label "non-TBC'd copy of Master" (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - American Society of Mechanical Engineers (Box 7)
      - Robotics and the Management Challenge, 1983; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Duration 51 minutes; Includes paper documentation used to explain the training video label reads "Robotics Master" (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
      - 1985, 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duration 28 minutes; Includes paper documentation used to explain the training video; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) Duplicates; labled "ASME Energy Copy" (Box 7, Folder 7-9)
      - Elevator Inspection (Box 7)
        - Unedited Footage, circa 1985; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) labeled "Part 1 Master" and "Part 2 Master"; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicates; labeled "Part 1 dub" and "Part 2 dub" (Box 8, Folder 1, Box 7, Folder 10)
        - Edited Version, circa 1985; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Independent Projects (Box 8)
    - Abstract Footage, Unedited, circa 1975; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) label states "Old Fort" (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Aerobis-t-r-e-t-c-h with Paula, Entire Program, 1985; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) label reads "rough cut of Aerobis-t-r-e-t-c-h with Paula for review purposes only, copyright Square 12 Video Copy (#3)" (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Angelique Martin, Talk Show Excerpt, 1984; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Duration 5.5 minutes (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Arts Mag: Avant-Garde Art, Entire Program, 1979; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duration 31 minutes, 20 seconds Title from tape label which reads "Tandoor Line Footage;" Index card with tape reads "Stan Gillila, Tom Johnson, Bill Viola 'Migration', Trisha Brown and Deborah Jewett, Ingrid Wiegand Executive Producer" (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Bob Towbin's B-Day Special, circa 1975; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duration 35 minutes (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Documentary Boat Ride in NY Harbor, Unedited Footage, 1988 July 4; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duration 2 hours Title taken from index card found with tape which reads "Documentary boat ride in NY Harbor, mentioned, unedited, original no titles;" title on tape reads "4th of July" (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Interview with Unknown New York Artist, Bolles, circa 1975; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Duration 12 minutes label reads "Bolles" (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Tandoor Line Footage, Unedited, 1982 July 26; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) label reads "Copy Tandoor Line Footage;" 1 audio track contains timecode (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - The Night Before The Night Before Christmas, 1976; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Duration 20 minutes, 11 seconds; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicates (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - Pamela Stockwell's Tompkins Square Police Riot (Box 9)
      - Edited Documentary, 1989; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duration 8 minutes, 30 seconds Index card states "Master Documentary video by Bob Wiegand, performance by Pamela Stockwell, Colette Miller, Peggy Vignon" (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Unedited Footage, 1988 October 12; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duration approximately 75 minutes Index card states "Original raw footage of Tompkins Square Police Riot Performance, Stockwell creating art piece First International Anathema Party Takeover, Lower East Side, Night club" (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Performance Documentation (Box 9)
    - ABC No Rio, East Village Performance Club Unedited Footage, 1988; 4 Videocassettes (VHS) Duration 8 hours labels read "ABC NO REO 1-4." Index card states"Document of East Village performance club owned by Matthew Courney, raw footage, open performances on Sunday nights. (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
    - Carolee Schneeman, Cat Torture I and II, 1989 May; 2 Videocassettes Duration 8 minutes (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Five Media Works Compilation Tape, circa 1980; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) label reads "Newrican Vil., Laura Foreman, Hisackika, John Watts performance, Wendy Chambers and Bill Rabinovitch, Trish Brown Dance Co. Spanish Dance." (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Laura Foreman, Line-Light Ensemble, 1988 June 6; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duration 25 minutes, 15 seconds Index card states "10 monitors in background, about sexually transmitted diseases, dancer in red tutu." (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Leonard Horowitz at ABC No Rio, 1989 January 15-22; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duration 8 minutes, 24 seconds (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Performance Compilation Tapes (Box 9)
      - Bob and Ingrid Wiegand, Compilation of Works, circa 1980; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duration 31 minutes, 30 seconds Side of tape label reads "Bob and Ingrid Wiegand Compilation Tape." Top of tape label reads "Tom Lillard 7:40, Bob/Ingrid Wiegand 7:30, Kirk Nurock 3:10, Trisha Brown 3:30, Pamela Stockwell 5:20, Leonard Horowitz 4:00." (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Performance Footage, Unedited, circa 1980; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) label reads "Performance" (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Performance Compilation, Unedited, circa 1980; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) 22 minutes label reads "Perf Comp." Index card reads " Performance Comp. Raw footage. Pamela Stockwell, Lenny Horowitz, ATOA?, One Night With You Horowitz Lower East Side Street Performance." (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Trisha Brown, Line-Up, circa 1977; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duration 7 minutes, 22 seconds label reads "Trisha Brown interviewed then performance of Line-Up." (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Work Samples (Box 10)
    - Work Samples, Clips Without Narration, circa 1985; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Duration 15 minutes Tape title reads "Video Demo #1" and tape label lists "Basic Electricity, Killian Setup, The Tenbe Bag, Snapshots for an Indian Day, Madama Butterfly." (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Work Samples, Video Narration without Clips, circa 1985; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Duration 10 minutes label reads "Demo Byte" (Box 10, Folder 3)
      First 10 minutes is the Demo Tape without the narration on "Demo #1", the rest of the tape is the remnants of Wiegand's Elevator training tape.
    - Work Samples, Clips for Teaching, circa 1985; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duration 11 minutes, 30 seconds. Tape label reads "Demo Teach Master." Index card found with tape states the contents "Nature, Bombay footage (Snapshots), Vocal group (ArtsMag), Dee Willis Genesis and Interview (Angelique), IBM, Nan Martin and The Sentence (NYU)."; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicate (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Works by Others (Box 10)
    - Eyes on the Prize, Commercial Production, 1986; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Mindset Video Titler M-1000, Sales Video, 1986; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Duration 10 minutes label is from "JVC Company of America" (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - New Jersey Nightly News, Calibration Tape, 1985; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Duration approximately 3 minutes (Box 10, Folder 7)